A Guide to the The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1813-1904, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters by and Related to Nathaniel Hawthorne
  - Subseries A: Dated Letters
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to George N. Sanders, 1854 February 1, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Sends payment for a telegraph bill and a note from Mrs. Hawthorne to Mrs. Sanders; explains that, given his demanding consular responsibilities, they cannot yet accept an invitation to visit. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, as Consul at Liverpool, to Stephen Pleasonton, 5th Auditor of the Treasury, 1854 August 25, LS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with an accompanying blank leaf, docketed. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Adds to, corrects, and expands upon his accompanying consular accounts for the fiscal quarter ended 30 June 1854; designated No. 14 at the head of the letter. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to F[rancis] Bennoch, 1854 August 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Introduces the letter's bearer, Mr. Geo. P. Bradford, an American friend, who also brings [James T.] Fields's gift of a silver fruit shovel for Mrs. Bennoch; hopes to see him soon. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [George N.] Sanders, 1854 November 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:10)
      Invites him and his wife and children to stay with the Hawthornes at Rock Park, Rock Park Ferry, for as long as needed while awaiting a steamer to New York. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to William A. Tiffany, 1854 November 27, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope. (Box-folder 2:11)
      Promises a fellow American his utmost support and protection following unnamed problems recently encountered; wishes him well on his Pacific voyage and return to friends. #6249-d.
    - Una Hawthorne [daughter of Nathaniel Hawthorne] to Horace [Mann, Jr.], 1855 January 31, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:12)
      A rambling, youthful account of the winter, books and apples sent by Mr. Fields, music and other studies, amusement at the account of Tom Thumb in Mr. Barnum's autobiography, and asks all about her young cousin Horace and his family in Ohio. #6249-a.
    - M[artin] Van Buren to Mr. [Nathaniel] Hawthorne, 1855 April 24, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:13)
      Encloses a note (not present) to Brown Shipley & Co. of Liverpool providing his return passage to the United States and requests that N.H. present it for him and reserve suitable accommodations for him and his son, Col. Van Buren, on the packet scheduled for June 30 (page 1 annotated in another hand with Room no 9... appropriated- best room in the vessel.. .) #6249-d
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Henry Wadsworth] Longfellow, 1855 May 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:14)
      Observes that the English are so enamored of Longfellow and his work that he (Hawthorne) has benefited from revealing their friendship and is sorry the poet is not coming soon to visit his devotees. Outlines his own plans to continue consular duties another year and then to spend a year or two on the Continent, made possible by supplementing his earnings in England with those from his writing. Then considers the later phases of a literary career, "Don't you think that the autumn may be the golden age both of the intellect and imagination?" As Longfellow's work grew steadily "richer and deeper," he hopes his own will. Also finds beneficial for Americans a residence in England, exposed to more "simple and natural people" and to ale and mutton, which may all perhaps be discernable in his next novel. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "My dear Sir," 1855 July 24, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:15)
      Refers to sending two letters of introduction for Mr. Stokes (?), not a personal acquaintance, to two American literary editors, Mr. [Evert] Duyckinck and Mr. [George] Curtis. #6249-a.
    - Sophia [Hawthorne] to Elizabeth [Peabody], 1855 August 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:16)
      Responds to recent letters, insisting on the general strength of her physical constitution, despite persistent and disruptive coughing, and the good care her husband gives. Comments on other family and friends: of Uncle George and Aunt Alice, recently deceased, and concern for their children, of her son Julian's whooping cough as well as his intellect and sensitivity, of the elderly Anna Parsons living on and on, and of Sarah Clarke's visit. Discusses Elizabeth's fine essay under revision and approves of her ceasing to teach school. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 January 26, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:17)
      Briefly reports that consular business has kept him from writing the preface promised to Miss [Delia] Bacon for her book on Shakespeare but will try to send it soon. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 April 9, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p., and a typed bookseller's description of the letter, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:18)
      Reports morning-after discomforts due to over-indulging in whiskey toddies served by Bennoch's friend Albert Smith during a visit with him in London. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Henry Wadsworth] Longfellow, 1856 April 12, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:19)
      Describes his experience with Albert Smith and others in Evans's Supper Rooms in London where the hospitable proprietor welcomed N.H. as a guest and hoped also to have Longfellow, Emerson, and Channing. This being but one instance of many he witnessed in which Longfellow was spoken of "with the highest interest and admiration," convincing him that his friend's literary reputation in London was at a peak, that it fairly demanded his visiting there, and that Hawthorne himself longed to see him. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 May 28, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:20)
      Forwards by Benoch cigars for the hospitable Lt. Col. Howell of the North Cork Rifles, the officer having once enjoyed smoking some with N.H. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 June 9, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:21)
      Fulfilling Bennoch's request that he supply a piece for Miss [Marguerite] Powers's annual [The Keepsake] had become a struggle following a period of writing inactivity, but he was sending a sketch revised from his journal, about a "pilgrimage" to a place he long fancied. Rejoices that Mrs. Hawthorne is soon arriving at Southampton and asks for Bennoch's recommendation of a temporary residence in Devonshire for her. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Miss Dodd, 1856 June 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:22)
      Thanking her for a note he just received after he greeted Mrs. Hawthorne in Southampton upon her return from a sojourn in Lisbon and Madeira. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "My dear Sir," 1856 June 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:23)
      Reporting on Mrs. Hawthorne's return to England, improved health, temporary residence near Southampton, and plan for a stay in London. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 June 30, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:24)
      Accepting Bennoch's invitation, announces his plan to leave the next day from Southampton with his whole family for a visit to Bennoch's home in London and requests directions. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne, as U.S. Consul at Liverpool, to the Collector of Customs, Port of Portsmouth, 1856 August 16, DS, partially lithographed and partially completed in manuscript, 1 p. on 1 l., docketed on the verso. (Box-folder 2:25)
      Endorsing Fredk. W. Brown as master of the ship Isaac H. Broadman. #6249-d.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne, as U.S. Consul at Liverpool, to Genl. Campbell, 1856 August 17, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, docketed on the verso. (Box-folder 2:26)
      Introducing Mr. J.P. Jones, from "your own State," made known to him by a letter of introduction from the Hon'ble. Jefferson Davis. #6249-d.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to Evart [sic] A. Duyckinck, 1856 September 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with the address clipped from the mailing envelope, mounted together on a sheet of heavy paper. (Box-folder 2:27)
      Introducing Mr. Martin, "son of the late celebrated artist" [Charles Martin?], and regretting having been away, in London, when Evert Duyckinck's brother George was in Liverpool. #6249-d.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 September 24, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:28)
      Imploring Bennoch's help in dealing with Miss [Delia] Bacon by acquiring for and sending to her a pamphlet on Shakespeare and by getting her book published somehow before she kills herself over it and worries him to death in the process. Also requesting clarification of the date of Bennoch's impending visit. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 September 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:29)
      Remaining uncertain about Bennoch's date of arrival but, should it be soon, directing him from Liverpool to their residence in Southport. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 September 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:30)
      Responding to Bennoch's intervening note, explaining that he and Mrs. Hawthorne were planning a three-months sojourn at Southport and that establishing the family there would preclude his accepting an invitation to Hereford, instead giving Bennoch instructions for visiting Southport. During that residence, Mrs. Hawthorne wishes to "try Miss Browne as governess," who, should she prove suitable, would be retained for service when they depart England, a prospect not yet to be discussed elsewhere. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 October 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with an envelope (doubtfully the original for this letter) and typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:31)
      Pointing out the surprising length of Miss [Delia] Bacon's manuscript, which he forwards to Bennoch, and which he hopes to persuade her to shorten but, regardless, intends to see published; finally, noting improvements in the health of both their wives. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [William] Ticknor, 1856 October 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:32)
      Replying briefly to Ticknor's recent letter, reporting on the benefits to Mrs. Hawthorne's health of Southport air and the governess's aid, Bennoch's continued travel in Germany, and uncertainty about where Ticknor might reach Miss Peabody. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 October 27, ALS, 5 pp. on 2 l., the first folded, with typed transcript, 2 pp. (Box-folder 2:33)
      Lamenting Miss [Delia] Bacon's erratic emotional reactions, her self-inflicted alienation, personally and financially, from her family in America as well as from himself, making a necessity of Bennoch's service as intermediary with her; his feeling more strongly about the importance of assisting her financially and editorially to get her Shakespeare book speedily published (by Messrs. Parker in England and Ticknor in America, the edition numbering one thousand copies of five hundred each, as he was hoping American sales might help him recoup English losses). #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 November 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:34)
      Returning Miss [Delia] Bacon's note and fully concurring with her that Hawthorne's name not appear on her book's title page, but thinking it appropriate to give it at the close of his introduction, his the composition of which would be aided if her text were forwarded to him as the pages were printed, since he had never had time to read her entire and "perplexing" manuscript. Additionally, encouraging Bennoch to see to his friend George Duyckinck in hospital after a railway accident. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 November 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 2 pp. (2 copies). (Box-folder 2:35)
      Accepting reluctantly the inclusion of his name on Miss [Delia] Bacon's title page, but insisting that it indicate that he contributed prefatory remarks only and that the title not absolutely deny Shakespeare's authorship [she argued for Bacon, Raleigh, and Spenser]. Otherwise, discussing household matters, such as the governess's limitations. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 November 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:36)
      Finding the assertiveness of Miss [Delia] Bacon's own introduction to her book certain to alienate readers; proposing a compromise- her allowing his introductory remarks to stand alone for his acceding to her title; finally, deciding in retrospect that involving Bennoch with so troubled an author was not justified, after all, by the substance of her theories. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 December 2, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:37)
      Insisting again that Miss [Delia] Bacon's introduction not appear in her book, that his alone suffice, and foretelling the blame she would heap upon them for it. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1856 December 23, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:38)
      Returning Miss [Delia] Bacon's letters to Bennoch, explaining that Ticknor expected little American response to his promotion of her book, and admitting that reading the printed text revealed her theory to seem more absurd than it had in manuscript, which challenged his skill to introduce it fairly without prejudicing readers. Closes with a report that his own family is well and wishes a happy Christmas to the Bennochs. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 February 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:39)
      Sending the manuscript of his preface ("painfully screwed out of a pre-occupied and unwilling mind") for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book, which is nearly done but for his paying the printer, and discussing use of his preface versus any introduction of hers. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 February 19, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:40)
      Acknowledging Miss [Delia] Bacon's disapproval of his preface for her book and his own preference for burning it rather than providing the full endorsement of her theories that she demanded. In a postscript, describing the recent nocturnal break-in and theft at their house, the second one during their residence in England. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 February 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:41)
      Insisting that his necessarily skeptical preface would prove too disadvantageous for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book and advocating that both his preface and his name be purged (" I would just as willingly be in the pillory as [on that title page]"). #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 February 28, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:42)
      Encouraging Bennoch to welcome completion of Miss [Delia] Bacon's book and to ignore her anger, but pointing out that her letters, far more interesting than her Shakespeare theories, would make a better book if they could but publish them. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 March 3, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:43)
      Considering a good title for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book but considering it hers to choose. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 March 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:44)
      Praising Bennoch for working out a book title with Miss [Delia] Bacon and discussing publishers. For a trip to Lincoln and environs, requesting advice on what and whom to see. For a trip to Scotland, urging Bennoch to join them, especially as he would resign his post in August. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 March 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:45)
      Discussing a modest English advertising budget for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book, payment for its printing, his expectation of losing money on the English edition, and Ticknor's hopes for some success in America. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 April 2, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:46)
      Sending a bank bill and promising a printer's draft for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 April 3, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:47)
      Sending the promised printer's draft for Miss [Delia] Bacon's book. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 April 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:48)
      Asking what London Chemist or Druggist might want to handle a new medicine he has received with credible endorsements from America and suggesting Bennoch and his wife try it. In a postscript, regretting the Athenaeum's negative notice of Miss [Delia] Bacon's book, the only one he has seen. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 June 13, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:49)
      Reporting news that Miss [Delia] Bacon shows signs of insanity, wondering what might save her, and considering that the "ill success of her book" has accomplished "what little remained to do, towards driving her mad." Renewing a plea that the Bennochs' join them on a tour of Scotland, and commenting on their pleasant trip to Lincoln and environs, during which he much extended his English journals but prepared nothing to publish. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne, as U.S. Consul at Liverpool, to the Collector of Customs, Port of Bath, 1857 July 1, DS, partially lithographed and partially completed in manuscript, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:50)
      Endorsing John Cole as master of the ship Holyhead. #6249-d.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 October 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:51)
      After his consular resignation, reporting that he awaits payment for his services before leaving England and urging that the Bennochs visit, whereupon they would introduce their American governess for comparison to the good English one who preceded her. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 October 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:52)
      Tiring of Leamington and soliciting lodging recommendations in London and Sydenham. Praising Bennoch for his kind assistance, upon which he has so often called. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1857 October 28, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:53)
      Explaining their lodging needs should last another two to four weeks. Wishing to depart for the Continent but stymied by financial uncertainty. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1858 March 16, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 2 pp. (Box-folder 2:54)
      To comfort his friend, sending his belief that Bennoch's fortunes surely will be restored. Reporting on their life in Rome, where his family enjoy visiting temples and churches, while he is ill, hates the place, and cannot write, which he must do to make expenses there. Planning to summer in Florence and return to Rome for the winter. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1859 July 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:55)
      Enjoying seaside Redcar in Yorkshire, with the children happy and his writing prospects good; requesting Bennoch give James Fields his address. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1859 October 8, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:56)
      In Leamington again, finishing his book [The Marble Faun] and hoping to see Bennoch there or in London. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1859 November 29, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:57)
      Reporting that his book at Smith & Elder is supposedly in press but doubts publication till spring, which is acceptable if they soon provide partial payment. Reporting also that J. Fields's has invited Mrs. Hawthorne to contribute to the Atlantic Monthly and teasing that she will be a rival "at bed and board," but truthfully that she prefers her normal role, "the best wife and mother in the world." #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1859 December 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:58)
      Disappointed that the Bennochs had not visited as planned and encouraging they do so after Christmas. Reporting on the printer's progress with his "Romance" [The Marble Faun], requiring his intervention in order to time English publication when it will not risk his American copyright. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 January 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, bound into a cloth folder. (Box-folder 2:59)
      Reporting that Mrs. Hawthorne has been confined with a bronchial illness from which she is now improving and that he looks forward to returning to America's drier air. Finding his book [The Marble Faun], in the printing phase, contains some "very nice writing" but pondering whether English readers will find it clever or absurd. Reiterating concern about protecting his American copyright if there is simultaneous publication in England and American. #6249-c.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 February 23, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:60)
      Reminding Bennoch, on behalf of Mrs. Hawthorne, that he promised to write and sending an ode or other verse for Una's birthday in March. Asking Bennoch to reserve a London hotel room for his imminent visit to Smith & Elder about transferring copyright [for The Marble Faun] to them. Promising that a copy of the finished book will be sent to him, although he hopes his friends will not read it. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 March 4, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:61)
      Thanking Bennoch for his fine poem celebrating Una's birthday and for praise of his book [The Marble Faun], noting that he would add explanatory text, should a second edition be published. Appealing for an assessment of Richmond's suitability for Mrs. Hawthorne's health as they choose a residence for their final months in England. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 March 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:62)
      Reporting that Bath accommodates Mrs. Hawthorne well. Sharing Ticknor's report of his book's success in America, where is was published properly as The Marble Faun, and adding that he has written an explanatory "Postscript" for Smith & Elder's second edition, perhaps compromising "its essential excellencies." #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to Julia E. Gibson, 1860 March 29, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:63)